well on this week's episode of smart
money we talk about how you can pick the
right health insurance and what are the
things that you need to do before you
select your insurance plan uh Girish n
nyak is with us Girish what are the you
know how is the procedure right how do
you select the right health insurance
plan yeah good question um there are
different kinds of individual uh
insurance plans that are available so
the first basic one which you understand
is the indemnity plan which typically
covers you when uh you are hospitalized
so your expenses during hospitalization
are covered by uh the plan there are
also what we call the benefit plans so
uh this kind of gives you a fixed payout
uh if you contract a certain illness
like for example a cancer benefit if you
contract cancer it'll pay out a lumpsum
amount which you take the insurance for
without going into whether you take the
treatment or not that's not UE but in in
the previous case in Indemnity uh you
have to actually get hospitalized and
take the treatment it is reimbursing
your actual costs there's also personal
accident policies which cover uh uh you
against accidents and all so that's uh
the different kinds of Health plant you
there the other uh aspect which is a
good one for typically need an Indemnity
plan definitely okay definitely need a
corate plans are mostly Indemnity plans
corporate plans are mostly Indemnity
plans uh which cover you for
hospitalization now Indemnity plans also
come with multiple you as a family uh
you can also purchase a what is called a
floater because uh when you take an
individual plan uh say you take a 10
lakh plan for an individual then it
covers you for 10 lakh but if you're a
family of for two adults two children
you can cover the entire family on a
floater for 10 lakhs then any one of
them incurring expenses of up to 10 lakh
is covered the total uh Family incurring
Expense of up to 10 lakh is covered so
it need not be an any one of them can
incur the expense it's covered so one
year someone can uh incur the expense
other year other one can multiple people
can incur the expense within the as long
as total is about 10 lakhs okay I have a
question here you earlier said that a
corporate plan uh a lot of generous
corporates sort of include your parents
also in the plan right but what happens
when if and when you leave the job uh to
your parents I mean you can take a
separate plan but largely this
individual plans don't include parents
who are above the age of 60 so what
happens then how do you uh safeguard
that so you have senior citizens plans
also okay so a lot of uh insurers have
plans for which cover senior citizens of
course the premium is a bit higher out
there uh naturally but uh that's
something that is available okay so uh
you can use a senior citizen plan to
cover uh parents again like I said
there's also a tax angle to it because
you cover your parents and up to 50,000
of Premium you can set off in your taxes
in your taxes okay and how do I settle
my insurance claims that is you know
because there's cashless there is
reimbursement uh a lot of corporates
have cashless uh Insurance processes as
well uh but what is the process like so
typically uh the cashless process works
for both corporate as well as individual
uh insurance claims so if the typically
if the hospital is within the insurers
Network then you can go to the hospital
and uh there'll be a TPA desk out there
where you given your papers and the uh
cashless approval is given by the
insurer and based on that the hospital
treats you without you having to pay out
any uh some up some from your pocket but
if that is not available you can also go
into reimbursement which is basically
you make the payment and then give the
bills to your insurer to reimburse you
for the cost you have incurred uh cash
is always better because you don't have
to Shell out anything from your pocket
and this and uh some I me we are we are
definitely offering a anywhere cashless
facility which is basically even if the
hospital is not within our Network so
our network is about 7,500 hospitals but
uh even if the hospital is not within
the network if you intimate us 48 hours
prior to your hospitalization then we
can arrange a cashless in that hospital
as well okay so that's a that's a great
benefit to uh to be associated with a
bigger brand like IC LOM at industry
level now we are having this initiative
where everyone is trying to move to a
cashless anywhere uh that should be out
soon but we we already had have had it
for almost a year now so you don't have
that stress of you know oh there's only
a certain amount of hospitals in your
list where you have to sort of you know
go and get your treatment or else you
won't get cashes so all that is going to
be uh sorted out yeah once we have this
uh cashless anywhere cashless anywhere
okay I want to understand different
scenarios right just real life examples
if I'm a 25y old if I'm a 33y old I'm a
40y old what is the kind of insurance
that I need so let's start with the age
of 25 in in that age group uh how much
Insurance do I need how much cover do I
need yeah we have a yeah typically uh uh
25y old I'm assuming single uh just
started off on the job uh would 7 and a
half lakh uh insurance would be good
enough of course there are tax benefits
which and that's 10,000 would be the
approximate premium including taxes uh
which one would have to pay so uh this 7
and a half lakhs you're saying is uh lar
corporate insurance has about 5 lakhs so
you're saying if someone is 25 and has a
5 lakh corporate insurance you have to
take an additional Insurance summer
short of it's better take insurance from
uh the beginning and what happens if you
don't claim the insurance then uh you
get uh bonus which is called additional
sum insured which gets added to the uh
cover some covered every year and
depending on the insurer this could go
up to uh 50 or 100% of the sum insurance
so if you're getting covered by
corporate insurance and you're not
claiming on this uh Insurance soon this
will with the additional sum insured
this could go up to 15 lakhs on its own
okay because of the additional sum
insured okay now let's move on to
someone who's say 33 years old has maybe
just got married or is planning to have
a child right what is the kind and is a
corporate employee what is the kind of
insurance that they need yeah I would
say that they would need to up their
cover a bit uh make it about uh 10 lakhs
and uh would have a floater policy
covering both uh self and spouse so that
would be uh better and of course you
would have add-ons because your
requirements would have increased you
would have a maternity benefit which
would be uh important again uh newborn
baby cover OPD some PL offer OPD not all
insures of op OPD because most of the
individual insurance is uh in patient
treatment that is you need to get
hospitalized but there are plans and
like we do have plans which offer uh
outpatient treatment which is basically
your consultation your Diagnostics your
pharmacist charges so uh you can buy OPD
add-on which covers all these uh
benefits so that is something that uh
they could cover on this okay let's move
on to the age group of say 45 to 60
right uh what is the kind of insurance
that they need and since that's an age
which is a tricky slightly tricky one uh
okay we have your 45y old businesswoman
who's married um that's a tricky one
because that's really the age when you
start developing some health issues as
well yeah so
how you like I said plan from before but
at this point in time you would
typically say have uh couple of kids so
two adults two kids uh 25 lakh policy uh
again uh is 25 lakhs enough these
days I'm just giving you a base you can
always there are policies which now
offer 50 1 CR yeah we have now launched
a unlimited coverage so oh really I
didn't know that okay we just launched
it okay what does that include it it's
all your everything but without a limit
for coverage okay so and so there's an
extra premium for that perhaps the
premium is higher obviously but uh for
again for those who can afford they can
buy that coverage and it covers you
worldwide as well okay so any cost
incurred when you travel anywhere again
like I said for this uh profile you'd
also need uh annual Health checkups so
if your plan offers you annual Health
checkups that should get covered because
at age of 45 you start doing your health
your health checkups more regularly than
when you are 25 right I know I know I
understand uh so what about retirement
right there are some people who have hit
the age of 60 suddenly developing a lot
of health issues but have no insurance
so what do they do we have here a 59y
old pensioner has pre-existing medical
conditions perhaps diabetes some even
have critical illnesses like cancer Etc
so what do they do if they don't have
insurance yeah so typically it's very
difficult if you have developed a
critical inness like cancer to get get a
policy okay um because that is a what
you call a non- insurable risk uh but if
you have diabetes if you have
hypertension there are policies that you
can get the premium will be higher and
again as a good practice again it's
always better to declare your
pre-existing illness to the insurer
before taking the policy okay that's a i
a lot of people uh undergo stress at
time of claims because they have not
declared or they forgotten to mention
any pre-existing ill and diabetes and
hypertension are the most common ones
that fall into this category someone
doesn't mention that uh he or she has
had diabetes when uh getting or has
hypertension and getting the policy when
it gets found out during a claim the
claim gets rejected and you have these
other issues that turn up so it's always
better to declare upfront uh because
there'll be some loading on the premium
but you'll get the policy so for uh uh
person who's retired without a policy
you would require a cover which
typically again has annual checkups you
would add the Outpatient Treatment OPD
because there would be lot of um at that
age you necessarily need to see the
doctor much more often than you see at a
younger age so that's a kind of policy
you would take with about 15 lakh cover
at least and a floater again for self
and spouse and that would be in the
range of about say 50,000 okay okay one
final question then um a lot of people
get sold ulips right so I mean I know
it's a very tricky topic but just
demystify it for us should people go for
your lips or not see I I am strictly
against it because I believe that your
investment should be absolutely separate
from your insurance perfect that's the
right way to look at it and that's a
life insurance uh link policy of course
of course health is health is separate
health is sold without a yeah without an
investment angle to it without in it's
protection for your investment I mean
that's how you look at it but for life
insurance for term insurance say for
example you think it needs to be a
separate policy all together term is I
mean you should take a Term Policy as
well because that is important but take
a Term Policy it's simple Insurance
that's uh that's that's so no to you
lips again investment and protection
should be separate okay that's what you
believe that's again uh to make it more
simple that that would be a but Health
we don't have that uh it's it's purely
protection uh look at it as protection
for your Investments and for your health
yeah oh okay all right G thanks a lot
for joining in appreciate you taking the
time out and speaking to CNBC TV8 with
that it's a wrap on Smart money thanks a
lot for
watching